In this video, we're going to go through
creative direction 101, [music] creative
direction specifically for personal
brands and personalities. We're going to
talk about the eras of creative
direction and why personal brands are so
important for this now as opposed
[music] to the entire art being very
brand-focused for the last two eras.
We're going to go through terminology.
I'm going to discuss the difference
between the strategy, content
operations, and creative directions. The
terms [music] get used interchangeably
quite a bit. We're going to zone in on
the personality era, how brands use
personalities and why they need to be
creative [music] directed by the brand.
World matters more than the account now.
Creating a content flywheel and
determining how to actually put content
out around personal brands from a
creative director perspective.
Distribution strategy and how to apply
creative direction principles to [music]
what personal brands do. And then get
into the actual sauce of how you apply
creative direction [music] techniques
around visuals, design, styling, and
world-building to personal [music]
brands. This is a topic that is near and
dear to my heart as someone who has
built my own personal brand but hundreds
of success stories come out of Cut 30.
And in particular, this last week I was
at Cannes Lions here in the South of
France. [music] I'm still in Nice right
now where creators and personal brands
were at the forefront of the world's
largest advertising [music] and
creativity festival. The entire industry
was gathered here and the number one
topic again and again in every room that
I was in was leveraging creators,
leveraging influence, building internal
teams around that in this new
personality [music] era we're in. I'm
inside this every day as someone who's
worked on this formally inside a brand.
I'm excited to share as much sauce as I
possibly [music] can with y'all inside
this video. Let's lock in. But first,
let's talk about the creative direction
eras. The era number one was the
original fashion and agency era. When
you thought of a creative director, you
would think of someone who worked inside
of a fashion house or someone who worked
at an agency. This was my first gig
inside this world. I was a graphic
designer who became a senior graphic
designer. I was at a smaller agency that
needed that differential. They were
trying to work with interesting clients.
At the time, we were with Red Bull, with
Vice, Grey Goose. We were doing events
in the Hamptons, at Super Bowl, at
Sundance. And the agency looked at
having creative direction as a
differentiator that they could bring to
their clients to say, "We think in an
interesting way about these ideas,
activations, and campaigns that you are
doing, and we can approach that, even as
a smaller firm, from a more unique,
culturally rooted perspective." But then
the term began to explode in what we
call the Virgil era, creative direction
2.0, where all of a sudden Hypebeast,
Highsnobiety, all of these cultural
publications that covered kind of the
streetwear revolution and the
streetwear's crossover into both luxury
and mainstream, and gave this huge
aspirational look at these designers, at
these creative directors, at these
brands that made thousands and tens of
thousands of kids around the world
aspire to have those kind of positions.
Prior to that, when I was growing up,
people wanted to be athletes, they
wanted to be musicians. In this era,
kids squarely began thinking about, "Can
I become a designer? Can I become a
creative director?" And you would see
things like Travis Scott with
McDonald's, Adidas collaborations,
Virgil working with Louis Vuitton. And
it opened up the idea of the field to be
something much more. Why wouldn't
McDonald's want to activate with a
creative director? Luxury brands wanted
to tap into streetwear. And in this era,
I'd recently become a VP of marketing. I
was working at a company called 3DR at
the time that made camera drones. And I
was managing a super talented creative
director who, inside of our company, was
the singular person who was giving
incredible ideation that separated our
campaigns and visuals at the time from
everyone else. For our launch film for
one of those products at the time, he
was the one who had the idea to train
actual apes to use the drone. We
executed that with all these 2001: A
Space Odyssey Easter eggs, had a very
viral launch video at the time, was
coming with concepts around everything
from our trade shows to our campaigns
that, as a hardware tech company, were
elevating us in a really competitive
scenario. But now we are in what I'm
going to call creative direction 3.0,
where the term has pretty actively lost
its meaning. You have real dilution of
what a creative director actually is.
We'll talk about that in a moment. But
we also have real solutions that need
creative direction. So here's what I
hear a lot. You see a lot of companies
and younger people who are hired into
that role. A lot of personal brands that
are hiring that role. Really, what
they're hiring for is a creative
strategist. I'll break down those terms
in a second. But, because everyone knows
what this role is, ideas, creativity,
personality, creating is now at the
forefront of marketing in the way it
wasn't 5 years ago, even 20 years ago.
It was still ads, campaigns, top-down.
Every brand now, from an up-and-coming
coffee shop to a tech company, to
traditional brands like fashion, all
need this creative to stand out, even
more so in the content era, and they
need more of it. But, because there's so
much of it, the term now means a lot of
different things to a lot of different
people. And, interestingly enough, for
the last year until about 60 days ago, I
was the creative director at a PE firm,
doing basically creative strategy across
brands inside their portfolio. There
aren't many PE firms with that kind of
job, but it makes sense, right? If you
are a forward-looking, and this company
was inside of beauty, you want to have
an edge across all the brands in your
portfolio, creative is a way to do it.
We're only going to see more of this.
We've seen it now with VC firms hiring
the same thing to represent both the
themselves and their firm, and also help
companies inside the portfolio. So,
there's more demand for it than ever.
And, why I made things like this video
is to give people the foundations of
what you would actually do to execute
this job. Because, it does mean a lot
more than that vague, unemployed term
you might see in someone's Instagram
bio. So, let's actually define these
different segments. So, first, when most
people see creative direction now, cuz
you'll see a lot of personal brands
hiring for it, for instance. You'll see
a lot of newer brands, or brands that
are running mostly meta, they're really
hiring for creative strategy. I'll very
directly define creative strategy as
someone who is bringing regular concepts
every single week for ads and/or can be
either one or both organic content.
They're doing ideation, they're making
briefs to get that ideation actually
executed by, whether it's external
creators, whether it's existing video
teams, or a personality they work for.
And, they're looking at analytics and
improving that flywheel. And, this is a
relatively new job in its popularity.
There are tons of people that are hiring
for it. Many of you I know were inside
the Motion Bootcamp that I was one of
the instructors on. They had 90,000
people in there. That's how many people
signed up for that boot camp. There were
thousands and thousands of people on
every call. Tons of people got jobs in
strategy after There's lots of tactical
application there, but that's not full
creative direction. Then we have content
operations. This is a really important
one. This is when you can do that
creative strategy. You can ideate. You
can help brief it to people. You can run
analytics and improve it. But you're
also starting to manage the schedule,
what gets produced when, you're
interacting with the people, you're
sending out the briefs, you're getting
it back, and you're managing the vendors
around it. We need new videographers. We
need new designers. I can pull that all
in there. That is an extremely valuable
job right now. The brands either have
from one person or they're recreating in
the aggregate, and personal brands do as
well. I have multiple people that work
on my team, including one I've just
brought on last week, working through
this kind of stuff. But then you get to
full creative direction, which includes
the above, right? You're still going to
be actually ideating. You're still going
to be briefing. You're still going to
live in the analytics. You're going to
more than ever need to know vendors, who
you can pull in. I can get this
photographer, that videographer. But
you're layering on the foundations of
determining, making the decisions around
the aesthetics, driving the entire
campaign versus the ideation on just
briefs, finding through lines across
these campaigns, building out what that
brand stands for, and then establishing
the world where the collaborators, the
people, the retail merchandising, all of
the intangibles. And that adds up to an
extremely complicated job, and one
that's ultra valuable. This brings us to
section two here, the personality era.
This used to matter most for brands.
This used to be something you'd apply
this art to brands, like you see in the
kind of the visuals here. You would have
collaborations. You would have massive
activations. Adidas driving around a
huge shoe, whatever it is. But brand
accounts, brand uh so like brand social
media, ad campaigns, these concepts are
useful, but matter less than ever on the
core. This is something I've had to
admit as someone who's worked on brand
social for a long time, was instrumental
in working with hundreds of brands now
over the last few years on their social
strategies, being able to look at it
being like, "You know what? The actual
account itself is not the the driver.
Now the world is the core driver." So,
what do I mean by that? The founder, the
team members, creators, and UGC people
who are making content for the brand,
influencers the brand works with, and
the customers all add up to
significantly more of a marketing push
than the brand accounts and ads
themselves in many cases. Now, if a
brand is spending a ton of money on ads,
potentially also even then, they're
using creators, UGC, and influencers for
that. Last week, I hosted a panel inside
the villa that we put together at Art of
Danny, who you see me collaborate with.
I had marketers from WhisperFlow and
ManyChat. We were doing it with software
company Motion, all focused on ad
strategy. And every single one of those
brands, that includes high-growth tech,
high-growth software, tons of consumer
goods, were recommending 30-plus percent
of someone's meta ad account should be
whitelisted, meaning they are running
ads from someone else's account. So, for
instance, you will see me doing
whitelisted ads with with my sponsors,
like Notion or ChatGPT, who run ads from
my account for their products. Shopify
is doing that on TikTok right now. With
30% of those ads at least being run on
that, being whitelisted as a best
practice by people that are on the edge,
shows you the importance of the
personalities that come up to a brand
even when it is ad-heavy. But, that
world matters so much now that it needs
creative direction. When before, you
could say, "Hey, I want to apply this to
the campaign, the big shoe, the collab."
Now, it's like, "Man, we need to get
great at how do we actually define this
for these team members?" And they all
need enablement, right? What do I mean
by enablement? So, working as a creative
director for that PE firm, one of the
big initiatives that that the core
company in the portfolio was doing was
sending out tons of mailers. Mailers to
creators so they want to make content
around their new launches. And the
design, look and feel of those mailers
would raise their efficacy, the creative
direction of them. The cooler and more
unique the concept is and how it looked,
the more likely it is to be made a video
about. And that post rate, how many
mailers we send out, do 20% of people
post or 60% of people post when you're
sending thousands a month, really adds
up. Creative direction is in the
enablement of content for the community.
And this goes a step further, too. In
another campaign recently, with a
company that has a creators that they
work with relatively regularly, we are
discussing how do we help them break out
of the current flow of content they're
in. One of the things we're doing is
giving everyone a budget to book a
luxury hotel room so they could film a
series of videos inside there to elevate
the look and feel of what they're doing
for a campaign that match that. So
you're saying, "Okay, we have 100
creators. We have a $400 budget per
additional one of those creators to then
elevate and have all of the campaign
footage around this look a different
way." Same thing with buying creators
Osmos, renting out studios where people
actually film it. If you saw the
production set up that we had at Can,
I'm creative directing my own channel,
right? Saying, "Hey, it makes sense for
me to be filming inside of a villa,
bringing in guests, having them see it's
high production, having it look and feel
elevated to tell the stories I'm trying
to tell." Same thing with brand trips or
sending people on trips around this
content. All of this adds up. These are
all creative directed elements inside of
personality strategy. And you will see
it even inside here. People represent
these brands. Doocey was probably one of
the best most prolific examples of this
I've used a lot where the people became
the representation of the brand. That is
happening all over now whether it's just
a face to a personality to some of
making the content. And you'll see all
the companies that are on the cutting
edge like Gentle Monster here was ahead
of those trends, ahead of the mailers,
ahead of all the things we're talking
about. Let's look at this concept of
personal brand 2.0. So personal brand
1.0 was attention. It was influence. How
can I just get people to watch my get
ready with me, how cool I look, what my
lifestyle is like. But now, this is the
repeated theme here Can, it's about how
do I make money, career growth, power,
intellectual influence, how do I learn?
All of a sudden, people that are making
content in our lives are giving us
significant advice about the things we
work on and replacing mentors, teachers,
and other things that have kind of gone
by the wayside in our current world that
anyone across the world can access
online. Obviously, I serve as a teaching
creator for a lot of people having learn
about the concepts of marketing,
creative direction, social media that
helps them in their brands and their
careers. That is a very different
personal brand era than beforehand if I
was just sharing if I'm walking around
France showing my glamorous life. Not
that glamorous.
>> Meanwhile,
>> I turned 40 this year and as serious
Below Deck consumers, my family is
celebrating by chartering a yacht around
Greece for 7 days. But now, to do this,
to do this well, and to continue to
elevate in the scenario, these people
need creative direction, right?
Everyone's videos look the same.
Everyone's doing yaps. How do you
determine a personality, right? Even the
fact that you've seen me across these
videos, now roughly 30% of my videos I'm
traveling inside of something. Hey, I
was just talking in London. Hey, I'm
here in Cannes. Hey, I'm on the boat in
Greece. You begin to learn and tell more
stories about me. But then, how do you
you're presenting that in a visual
field? I had a creative director being
like, "Hey, let's look at this in an
incredible visual aspect." How do you
turn those into campaigns? These are the
things that all personal brands and any
brand that has people representing them
need to start thinking about. Applying
this on a smaller tactical level. Let's
actually get into some tactics here. I'm
going to talk briefly about content. I
have a million videos about content if
you want to actually dive deep into
that, so we're not going to get into
tons on like hooks and stories and stuff
like that. I will give you a format for
actually working with a planning inside
that niche. Then we're going to get into
thinking through distribution strategy.
And then we're going to get into the
like creative direction tactics portion.
So, first, when you're coming up with
content for this, a big part of creative
direction for personal brands isn't just
like, "What does the photo shoot look
like?" It's helping them make content,
right? What is the YouTube video? What
is the LinkedIn post? What is the
Instagram video? How do you create
ideation for that? And so, this comes
from having recurring topics that you
talk about, from having recurring
formats, like types of yaps. I have a
whole yapping video if you want to get
into that. But hey, I make content in
front of a whiteboard. I make vlogs
where I go around. These are all formats
and things that creative directors
should understand and be able to give
people access to. Most importantly, it's
stories. What are the events, people,
and products that you can tell stories
about? What happened in either my brand
arc or my arc or something in history
that's able to be talked about. What are
people in history that inspired me or
are worth talking about or that I'm
collaborating with now that I can tell
stories at and around? And what are
products? Let's an unboxing video or
something you are developing or
something that got released, the five
things you're going on a trip with, or
whatever it is. That becomes the
framework that creative directors for
personal brands need to be able to bring
to any scenario. How can we actually use
topics around those to engage and build
content plans? Like I mentioned, I'm not
going to cover scripting heavily in
this. So, I want to I'll on the creative
direction portion at the end. But the
best thing you can do, if you are doing
the strategy for yourself, if you have a
personal brand, or if you are a
strategist or creative director you're
working with a client, is a twice
monthly meeting, every 2 weeks, and do
this exact flow. And if it's you, if
you're the personal brand, hire a
strategist or a writer. It's important
this is conversational. You don't want
to do this just by yourself. How I'll do
it is I will make sure Granola is on as
an AI notepad, and I have a conversation
about news in the niche. But, how do you
get news in your niche? So, I have
Perplexity send me a report every week.
You can follow aggregation accounts and
make a list. There's tons of curators
and stuff like that. LinkedIn news, if
you're doing more generic business, is
excellent when you log in on desktop.
They have a bunch there, and that's also
a bit of a cheat code because they
weight the topics in those news higher
in the algorithm. The editorial team
curates additional posts to attach to
the topic. I won't get too deep into
that. But, basically, looking at all the
news that's out there in the world and
going, "Do we like this, or do we
dislike it? Can we share an opinion on
that? Is there enough [clears throat] of
an opinion to share, or can we share a
tactic on that?" Easy way to go through
interpretation of the news. Then, look
at personal history. What happened since
our last meeting? What's in your camera
roll? This is great if you're working
with If you're looking back at your
history and wondering what to write
about, look at this last week. Okay,
what happened? Is there anything in my
camera roll that inspires a story or an
anecdote? Okay, now go back 1 year.
Apple makes this really easy on the
phone, or any phone, really. So, you go
back 1 year. What was happening 1 year
ago? Is there any stories you can tell
from the couple weeks around that time
period? Same thing with 3 years, same
thing with 5 years. Cuz you'll notice a
lot of the stories of where you came
from. "Oh, I was developing this thing.
Oh, I worked on X and Y. This is when I
was living in this. Oh, here's a lesson
with a co-founder I broke up with."
Whatever it looks like. Those become
really compelling stories. And just
having that process where every 2 weeks
you're going back through that and
looking into your history starts a lot
of good conversations. Then, pull from
video database. You can go look at by
topic winners. You can go real estate,
marketing, whatever it is. You can look
at videos that are outlier performers
from the last period of time. If that
inspires topics. Then, another one is
ask Meta AI. Meta AI is super
underrated, and it's a free app. You ask
for viral formats that a handle should
consider. I can go in there and be like,
"Hey, I'm Orme's World. I'm traveling in
Nice. What topics have been hitting
around here? What would you suggest for
me based on my existing content? It's
actually quite good. So the job is to
discuss with people back and forth in
person and debate around these. Would
this make a good video? What could the
hook be? What could the angle be? And
that conversational back and forth
sparks really good ideas. And then
Granola is mad useful for this because
while you have this conversation, like
it's not a meeting bot, there's no bot
in there. It transcribes audio directly
whether you're in Zoom, you're in Google
Meet, Slack huddle, or if you're in
person sitting down and doing it. And it
does AI enhanced notes, so it writes it
like a notepad. So it's like a shorthand
clean full summary of the conversation.
And then there's recipes. This is why I
use this. There's pre-built prompts that
can work before or after the meetings.
And so I could say, "Hey, I want a full
list of script and hook ideas." I can
basically have that as a recipe I run
after every planning session. It's going
to give me a list out of all the ideas
that we had. But what I would do is I
would then very quickly be like, "Is
this a priority? Is this a backburner?
Is this a middle?" We'll just tier them.
And a lot of people are using ChatGPT
and Claude for like brand voice. You can
integrate Granola with its MCP
connector, so it's a reference. And all
these meetings that you do, if you have
that and you're in a project for a
particular client or your own, it will
just pull in all those topics and ideas
that you already have. It's completely
integrated. You can learn more about
Granola in the link in my description.
They are the sponsor of this video and
one of the recurring ones. I appreciate
them for being an excellent piece of
software. And as a meeting, you should
absolutely be running inside strategy
like this. Today I want to shift to
distribution before we talk about
tactics. So what do I mean by
distribution? So brand creative
directors had retail merchandising. What
happens and shows up in the stores. They
had the runway and the runway shows.
They had the physical trade show booths.
That still applies to this world, too.
What does the merchandise look like?
Like the Marty Supreme campaign being an
excellent example of that. Pharrell's
Human Race and Adidas with a new
smoothie store, another kind of example.
Okay, you're building like a
collaborative world here. But now inside
the personal brand era, that's every
social network. That's part of your
distribution. That could spill into the
physical world. What are events, right?
I had four tour dates earlier this
month. I just did a villa in Cannes. We
had merchandise for all of those. You
could get bags. The Dark Room Villa with
Orange on. The The hats, matches,
towels. It's a whole kind of setup built
around this like murder mystery 70s 60s
brand world that we were building. All
of these concepts that I understand from
traditional creative direction just get
ported over into what these new channels
look like. Getting into the sauce and
the sauce is like the good [__] right?
This is what like the internet bro
consultant types will never be able to
get that if you're a real creative you
can dive into and have. Because what I
see all the time is people that call
themselves a creative director that
hired for a personal brand or coming up
with ideas and scripts that don't have
the ideas. They don't have like this
toolkit that I'm going to talk about
right here that allows you to make hot
[__] So first is these ideas of like
sets, visuals, lighting, right? I'm
filming this here not in front of the
white background wall. All of those
things help tell a story. How do you set
those up? How do you use them as
recurring bits? How do you change that
as part of the narrative? That is part
of the creative direction of personal
brand. Then same thing with your design,
the colors, the fonts, the lock-ups, the
titles for your series. What do those
say? How do you have those repetitive?
How do you build those out into a brand
kit? If you even take those, if you take
a personal brand that's making content
right now or experts for a brand and
everything's going kind of mid and you
go, "Hey, we're going to dial in the set
to really tell a story and be visually
eye-catching on feed, then we're going
to lock in our specific fonts and color
patterns in a way that's sick. We're
going to have our repetitive series.
We're going to make cool lock-ups for
them with animations." You know, that's
the basics like tactical stuff of making
higher-end content, but it will
immediately elevate the performance of
what a lot of that looks like. Then
styling, another huge one and rather
underrated. What are people wearing and
why? What does that say? How does that
get put together? Applying those same
principles to personal brands, to UGC,
etc. is important. I don't know how many
times I've told people in Cut 30,
there's two scenarios. One is the guys
who've never had to care about their
appearance before who are like, "Hey,
just clean yourself up a little bit like
put on a nice shirt and your content
will go a lot better." Female creators
can kind of make the choice and can go
either way of like, "Hey, you can go all
in and like fully glam up and that will
get you a particular audience." Or you
can go the opposite of that and say,
"I'm going to take it completely natural
or candid or casual." which tells a very
different story. You have to think about
how those approaches go and they're very
powerful. Then we have the world
building, collabs, interviews. Personal
brands engaging with other personal
brands are signals to the algorithm and
they're also signals to the consumer.
You see, every month I try to collab
with a different person, right? I
collabed with someone when I'm out here
in Europe, we were doing a luxury
Italian villas for sales, investment
properties. Made a collab on something I
knew nothing about with a creator from
Cut 30 who I enjoyed, who we made a
video together. Now, before that, I had
a collab about collabs with Bima
Williams. Did a buying guide with Hans
Loraie, right? You continue to interact
with each other's worlds and build up
the people that you know, even in the
events, right? So, in Cannes, I put
together a house with a bunch of other
creators. We had Sammy Cohen, Dara
Denney, Ashwin, bunch of small and
up-and-coming creators. JT Barnett was
in there, too. And we're all together
making content, hosting events together,
living in a place for a few days, and
building that world that we all interact
with each other and know with each
other. That is part of personal brand
world building. And with brands, it's
especially important because you have
all these personalities and influencers
and founders, and you can use each other
to lend each other credibility. And
then, treating actual launches like
campaigns. It's the same thing with
personal brand. You want to follow if
you've seen my art of the marketing
campaign video, where it's like, "Hey,
how are we going to tease this? How are
we going to unveil it? What's the actual
launch? And how do you sustain it?"
That's the same thing for a creator
launching a podcast. That's the same
exact thing for a personal brand that's
playing a part in a launch. All of this
follows the same playbook, focused on
for personality. And I just want to
highlight that if you are thinking like
this, and you want to apply this to
personal brands, you can be ahead of the
wave. And what's also nice about that is
there's so many personal brands to get
started. One of the common questions I
get is, "How do I even get started with
creative direction?" And it's hard,
right? I always recommend you need to
have a core skill first. You need to be
a designer, a video editor, a
copywriter. Have some kind of core
creative skill that you then layer that
on top of. But really, you need to have
that strategy component. You need to be
able to brief, ideate, do those things I
broke down in content strategy to
content operations to creative
direction. But doing that for a brand
requires a lot of trust. For a personal
brand, it's a much lower standard,
right? Cuz if you do that for someone
with 50,000 followers, you're still
doing all those motions, you're still
briefing, you're still ideating. Maybe
you're getting paid significantly less,
but you are getting the experience to
move it up. That's why I like this era,
cuz it gives so many more people the
ability to say, "Yeah, for $1,500 a
month, or five grand a month, or
whatever it is, I'm working on creative
direction for these personalities, or
for UGC creators, for a brand, or for an
influencer." And you're building that
toolkit that you can then continue to
use to level up and learn, cuz there
aren't a lot of opportunities to to to
those jobs otherwise. And we are ahead
of the game here. And I had done a test
for those of you that were on my last
community call, you heard about this. I
ran a content operations one-week boot
camp in June that we sold out. We had 50
people in there. I was only doing 50
slots. We did basically a one-week
sprint. We were like, "Cool, we're going
to develop front to back end a plan,
whether it was your personal brand or a
client's personal brand." Working
through all the content ideation and
formats, working through a plan for how
you were going to creative direct
visually for the next 90 days. Basically
like a concrete mechanism for it. I was
surprised at the popularity, how fast we
sold it out, and then how many people in
there to apply it, then asking for more,
right? This is just an introduction of
this. Because there's just not much
information out there, but that's alpha
for people that are selling freelance
services, right? Or for creatives who
want to make a step in their careers
seeing where that trend is going and
getting ahead of it. I am going to be
doing that evergreen now, so like you're
not in the one-week format. I'm just
going to have that all available with
like the Slack community that we have.
You can learn more about that below as
well. But I just wanted to introduce the
concept inside of this. If you liked
this kind of one-on-one overview, I have
a full [music] advanced career direction
video prep for this. So let me know if
that's interesting or if you're going
too deep. And shout out Granola, you can
learn more about them in the
description. And thank y'all as always
so much for watching.